<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" 
    xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    >
    <channel>
        <title>Reilly Spitzfaden, Composer</title>
        <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog</link>
        <atom:link href="https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <description>A blog about my personal interests, including C++ audio plugin development, composition/sound design in Max/MSP, open tech, and web development</description>

        <item>
            <title>New Album Announcement</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/04-05-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/04-05-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 EDT</pubDate>
            <description>My trio 'If this reaches you' is on Apply Triangle's new album, out on April 12!</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                <h2>New Album Announcement</h2>
                <p>One of my compositions is on an upcoming album &mdash; <a href="https://applytriangle.bandcamp.com/album/oxalis-triangularis-vol-2"><cite>Oxalis Triangularis: Vol. 2</cite></a> by <a href="https://applytriangle.com/">Apply Triangle</a>! The ensemble is a NYC-based electroacoustic trio comprising Yoshi Weinberg (flutes), Tyler Neidermayer (clarinets), and Jixue Yang (piano/keyboards).</p>
                <p>The full album is a <a href="https://applytriangle.bandcamp.com/album/oxalis-triangularis-complete-volumes-1-3">3-disc set</a>, and my piece &mdash; <cite>If this reaches you</cite> &mdash; will be on <a href="https://applytriangle.bandcamp.com/album/oxalis-triangularis-vol-2">volume 2</a>.<br />
                It comes out on April 12, and you can pre-order in digital and CD format now!</p>
                
                <h3>Composing <cite>If this reaches you</cite></h3>
                <p>When I wrote the piece, I had recently discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software-defined_radio">software-defined radio</a>. I use an <a href="https://www.rtl-sdr.com/about-rtl-sdr/">RTL-SDR</a> receiver — a small USB dongle that contains a tuner and ADC chip — and the tuning and demodulation is handled in the computer, using software like <a href="https://www.sdrpp.org/">SDR++</a> or <a href="https://airspy.com/download/">SDRSharp</a>.</p>
                <p>The receiver can pick up analog voice communication (e.g., ambulances, air traffic controllers, etc.), and digitally-encoded transmissions such as pagers, clock synchronization signals, and weather map faxes. Fun fact: the background image for my site is one such weather fax! The digital communications sound something like a <a href="https://freesound.org/people/wtermini/sounds/546450/">dial-up modem</a>, and work in a similar way. The analog voice sounds crackly and staticky, and I can often hear sounds in the background, giving fascinating, but extremely limited glimpses into what's happening on the other end.</p>
                <p>Especially in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shortwave_bands">shortwave bands</a>, the signals I picked up often came from great distances — at one point, I picked up a station from Japan. As I listened, I felt both connected to all the signals' sources, but also a great sense of distance and loneliness. As I found ways to combine the radio sounds with unusual and experimental sounds from the instruments, the radio sounds strongly evoked memory, loss, nostalgia, and distance for me.</p>
                
                <h3>Technical Notes</h3>
                <p>To play the radio sounds, I made a Max/MSP patch for the pianist that assigns radio samples to the lower keys, and has a bright, electric piano sound on the higher ones. The clarinetist plays a variety of <a href="https://heatherroche.net/category/multiphonic/">multiphonics</a> and other extended techniques, and the flutist also has a cardboard box to scrape with a cello/bass bow.</p>
                
                <h3>Program Note</h3>
                <p>I wrote a short poem as a program note for the piece:</p>
                <blockquote>
                <p>I watched the space between the houses undergo a sea change<br />
                Into something slippery and strange<br />
                Though it wasn’t mine to hold, I still carry it with me</p>
                <p>I walked as far as daylight would take me<br />
                The wires stayed the same<br />
                I brought them back anyway to show that I had done my due diligence</p>
                <p>A satellite floated overhead today and reminded me of home</p>
                <p>I can hear it now<br />
                I am not the only one left to tell the tale</p>
                <p>A letter came, but the sky had already touched the ground behind me, so I kept walking</p>
                </blockquote>
                
                <h3>The Project</h3>
                <p>Here's the announcement from the ensemble:</p>
                <blockquote>
                <p>Announcing <cite>Oxalis Triangularis</cite> &mdash; a triple album of thirty-three new works from thirty-three composers recorded in a fully remote setting by Apply Triangle. The project was developed through a call for scores in the summer of 2020 and stems from the resilience of artists to continue to create through a global pandemic. It is a testament to the flexibility and creativity possible through electroacoustic composition.</p>
                <p>Oxalis Triangularis refers to the scientific name for a purple “false shamrock” due to its triangle-like leaves. Throughout three albums Apply Triangle not only showcases the innovative techniques of 33 living composers but also highlights the embodied cultural nuances inherent in each composer’s style.</p>
                </blockquote>
                <p>Thanks for reading, and I would love if you check out the album!</p>
            ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>RSS Is Nice</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/03-10-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/03-10-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
            <description>My process of adding RSS to my blog, my rediscovery of how nice RSS is, and some music blogs I've been enjoying</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                <p>This past week I added <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS">RSS</a> to my blog! Here I'll talk about the process of doing that, my rediscovery of how nice RSS is, and some music blogs I've been enjoying. If you want to follow my blog, <a href="https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/feed.xml">here's the link</a>.</p>
                <h3>RSS for my Blog</h3>
                <p>I started out by trying to make my blog automatically generate the RSS feed — all I would have to do is upload the files to Netlify as I normally do. The first place I looked was at this <a href="https://www.contentful.com/blog/generate-blog-rss-feed-with-javascript-and-netlify/">article</a>, with the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/jsdom">jsdom</a> NPM package to handle parsing my HTML files where this post used <a href="https://www.contentful.com/about-us/">Contentful</a>'s built-in system. As I tried this and some related avenues out, I became unhappy with the number of steps involved, and auto-generating started to feel like more work than simply hand-writing an XML file.</p>
                <p>When I looked into it, I found that hand-writing an RSS XML file was even easier than I assumed, and didn't hinder my wanting to make new posts. The <a href="https://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification">RSS specification</a> is all clearly laid out, and the official page includes <a href="https://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification#sampleFiles">sample files</a> for v0.91, v0.92, and v2.0. My current system is that I have a <a href="https://github.com/reillypascal/personalsite/blob/main/reillyspitzfaden/blog/templates/template.xml">template</a> in my site files, and I can copy/paste the <code>&lt;item&gt;</code> section into the main feed file and fill in the blanks.</p>
                <p>This method is still a little "rough-and-ready," what with the copy-pasting, but the important thing for me is that it <em>works</em>. After seeing Molly White <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@molly0xfff/111960696197094015">mention</a> it, I have been eyeing the IndieWeb wiki's discussion of <a href="https://indieweb.org/content_management_system#Why_write_your_own">making your own CMS</a>, and I may try improving my system with something like that — not integrated with Netlify, but I could run a homemade static site generator before uploading my files. My best guess so far is I could use the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/rss">rss</a> NPM package as one way of handing the RSS part of a CMS, but if people have suggested tools, I would love to hear about them!</p>
                <p>Side note: one final tweak I did outside of RSS is adding a typographical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asterism_%28typography%29">asterism</a> to my blog posts, inspired by jamesg's recent "<a href="https://jamesg.blog/2024/02/19/personal-website-ideas/">100 things you can do on your personal website</a>" post.</p>
                <h3>Why RSS</h3>
                <p>For a while I would follow news outlets on social media and look for stories there, but I've found that this makes using social media feel like playing Russian roulette — I never know if I'm going to see something funny a friend posted, some cool new music, or an atrocity I have no control over. Separating out my news so I have more choice over what to read and when means I'm much less anxious, while still staying engaged with what's going on around me.</p>
                <p>In addition to giving me more control over what I see and when, and helping me keep track of a large number of sites, one thing I especially like is how clean the interface can be, and how I get to decide how it looks. I use <a href="https://netnewswire.com/">NewNewsWire</a>, and when I open an article, it's just text and maybe a few images, and everything is formatted the same. The list of articles too — articles are linearly organized, rather than scattered around the page. The whole experience feels much quieter and more relaxed.</p>
                <h3>Favorite Blogs</h3>
                <p>I follow a variety of things, but one area that's been especially nice is experimental music. I spent the past year or two listening to mostly the same music (such as <a href="https://autechre.bandcamp.com/album/draft-730">Autechre</a>, <a href="https://fire-toolz.bandcamp.com/album/rainbow-bridge">Fire-Toolz</a>, and <a href="https://magdalenabay.bandcamp.com/album/mercurial-world">Magdalena Bay</a>), but being in Fediverse/IndieWeb circles, I've stumbled onto a bunch of blogs and artists that give me a huge amount of new music to explore. It took me a bit of time in these circles, but when I found the first few blogs or artists, I came across countless others in rapid succession, often as a result of previous blogs or artists. Here are some of my favorites:</p>
                <ul>
                <li><a href="https://acloserlisten.com/">a closer listen</a><ul>
                <li>This site focuses on instrumental album reviews. I appreciate that the <a href="https://acloserlisten.com/staff/">writers</a> are numerous and prolific — I get reviews in my inbox every day. <a href="https://acloserlisten.com/rss">RSS</a></li>
                </ul>
                </li>
                <li><a href="https://avantmusicnews.com/">Avant Music News</a><ul>
                <li>AMN has been a particularly helpful jumping-off point. They do a mixture of their own reviews and sharing reviews from other sites. They describe themselves as covering music that's "challenging, interesting, different, progressive, introspective, or just plain weird" — exactly what I like to hear. <a href="https://avantmusicnews.com/rss">RSS</a></li>
                </ul>
                </li>
                <li><a href="http://www.onthefringesofsound.com/">Fringes of Sound</a><ul>
                <li>A blog that covers "independent experimental, ambient, noise, and other music that falls well outside the mainstream." I haven't been able to find out as much as some of the others, but the Instagram page lists just one person, a <a href="https://www.instagram.com/lars_haur/">Lars Haur</a>, so this may be a single-person project. <a href="https://www.onthefringesofsound.com/feeds/posts/default?alt=rss">RSS</a></li>
                </ul>
                </li>
                <li><a href="https://www.outsidenoise.org/reviews/">Outside Noise</a><ul>
                <li>I had known about this blog for a while, but I found that keeping my news and blogs in a bookmarks folder and having to repeatedly check to see if anything new was posted discouraged me from reading. I also find managing bookmarks on my phone to be especially irritating, and unfortunately, if I don't have something on my phone I'm less likely to check it. <a href="https://www.outsidenoise.org/reviews?format=rss">RSS</a></li>
                </ul>
                </li>
                <li><a href="https://yeahiknowitsucks.wordpress.com/">Yeah I Know It Sucks</a><ul>
                <li>This one I had actually encountered back in 2018 when they did a <a href="https://yeahiknowitsucks.wordpress.com/2018/01/04/how-things-are-made-with-reilly-spitzfaden-jamie-vandermolen-maurice-rickard-and-an-eel/">review</a> of an album that included one of my pieces! I was reminded of the blog when another blog (I feel like it was AMN, but I can't find the post) linked to a review by Yeah I Know It Sucks, and I saw that they have continued regular coverage of interesting music. <a href="https://yeahiknowitsucks.wordpress.com/rss">RSS</a></li>
                </ul>
                </li>
                </ul>
                <h3>Final Thoughts</h3>
                <p>That's all for today! I'm looking at adding some new features to my site (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webmention">Webmentions</a> are high on my list), and I'm continuing to do sound design and composition. When I get more interesting sounds made or site features added, I'll definitely do a writeup of those here as well.</p>
                <p>I've also been getting back into reading for fun, now that I'm out of school (finished my composition PhD in 2022), and I may discuss some of the books I'm reading. I recently got "<a href="http://www.kristengallerneaux.com/high-static-dead-lines">High Static; Dead Lines</a>" by Kristen Gallerneaux, "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Leaves">House of Leaves</a>" by Mark Z. Danielewski, and "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Is_How_They_Tell_Me_the_World_Ends">This Is How They Tell Me the World Ends</a>" by Nicole Perlroth, and I'm excited for all of them.</p>
            ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>Listening and Reading List — Mar. 1, 2024</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/03-01-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/03-01-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
            <description>Links and discussion of what I'm currently listening to and reading</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
                <h3>What I've been listening to</h3>
                <ul>
                    <li><a href="https://patrickcarey.bandcamp.com/album/collapse-etiquette"><em>Collapse Etiquette</em></a>, by Patrick Carey
                        <ul>
                            <li>Both aggressive/noisy and ambient. There are bright additive and saw synths, and a bunch of intense, percussive, glitchy noise. Each of the 9 tracks maintains a consistent energy &mdash; always the same material, but always different, like the motion of a mobile. Overall, the album reminds me of tuning a radio through a "new age" station with poor reception, and I found it inspiring for my own work.</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>"<a href="https://alexanderpanos.bandcamp.com/track/cycles-2">Cycles</a>" by Alexander Panos
                        <ul>
                            <li>I first discovered him via his "<a href="https://payhip.com/b/h9l7V">Color Transfer</a>" Max for Live bundle, which makes some very cool sounds. This track is heavy on the granular sounds and "mulched-up" drums, but it also has poppy and traditionally "pretty" chords and vocals, and moments where the meter becomes clear. A beautiful and unique piece.</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <h3>What I've been reading</h3>
                <ul>
                    <li>Nathan Ho's <a href="https://nathan.ho.name/posts/cepstrum/">blog post</a> on creative uses of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cepstrum">cepstral</a> processing.
                        <ul>
                            <li>I've been interested in doing this in my own sound design, but FFT processing in Max is one area I need more work. Nathan uses SuperCollider, and while I like what it can do, I prefer to write for other people to perform, so I like Max's ability to make robust GUIs for my performers. This post looks like it will be helpful in understanding the cepstrum and using it in Max.</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Tom Coates' <a href="http://plasticbag.org/archives/2024/01/how-threads-will-integrate-with-the-fediverse/">post</a> on how Threads will integrate with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse">Fediverse</a>.
                        <ul>
                            <li>I'm intensely torn on Threads, Bluesky, potential Tumblr <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ActivityPub">ActivityPub</a> support, etc. I love the Fediverse; I would like to interact with as many of my friends as possible on it; and Cory Doctorow's <a href="https://www.versobooks.com/products/3035-the-internet-con"><em>The Internet Con</em></a> has gotten me excited about interoperability, so on one hand, I would like as many things as possible to connect to the Fediverse. On the other hand, part of what makes the Fediverse great is the non-commercial nature, and I don't want Meta to "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embrace,_extend,_and_extinguish">embrace, extend, extinguish</a>" it.</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>

                <h3>What I've been doing</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>The W3C <a href="https://indieweb.org/Social_Web_Incubator_Community_Group">Social Web Incubator Community Group</a> (which includes stakeholders such as Meta) was brought up at Wednesday, Feb. 28's IndieWeb <a href="https://indieweb.org/Homebrew_Website_Club">Homebrew Website Club</a> Pacific meeting. A member mentioned that at one meeting, there was discussion of <a href="https://github.com/Letterbook/FEP/tree/web-based-protocol-handlers">extensions</a> to ActivityPub, and that he was able to voice concern that this could lead to an "embrace, extend, extinguish" situation. It looks like anyone can join the mailing list and meetings (see <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/socialcg/">this</a> page), and I will be joining today. It does encourage me that there is this way for the Fediverse community to get involved and help shape the future of ActivityPub.</li>
                    </ul>
                ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>Composition Journal — Feb. 27, 2024</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/02-27-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/02-27-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
            <description>Spectral compositing sound design from my work-in-progress "Forget your name"</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
            <p>I'm currently working on a piece for (tentatively) B-flat clarinet; MIDI keyboard/Max; and a percussionist playing a mix of standard instruments, "junk," and feedback setups.</p>
            <p>One of the sound design techniques I've been enjoying lately is making a "spectral composite" of two sounds using Eric Lyon's "<a href="https://github.com/ericlyon/FFTease3.0-MaxMSP">FFTease</a>" Max/MSP package. I'm using the <code>fftz.ether~</code> object, which:</p>
            <ul>
            <li>Takes the FFT of two sounds</li>
            <li>Compares the corresponding bin between the two FFTs</li>
            <li>Takes either the louder or quieter of the two, depending on the settings</li>
            <li>The choice can also be "weighted" toward one source or the other</li>
            </ul>

            <p>I particularly like the effect of taking the quieter of the two. It's great for combining a more sustained sound and one with a percussive envelope. As the percussive sound decays, more and more of its bins "win out," imparting a percussive envelope on the output.</p>

            <h3>Sound 1: tonal/sustained</h3>
            <p>For today's sound, my sustained, tonal source was made with the open-source <a href="https://surge-synthesizer.github.io">Surge XT</a> synthesizer. Surge XT contains an oscillator titled "Twist" that appears to be an implementation of Mutable Instruments' "<a href="https://pichenettes.github.io/mutable-instruments-documentation/modules/plaits/">Plaits</a>" Eurorack module. I'm using one of the organ-like wavetables to create a sound that rapidly morphs between low and high harmonics. Additionally, Surge XT supports microtuning, and I'm using the 131313... mode of <a href="https://en.xen.wiki/w/20edo">20-edo</a>.</p>

            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/plaits_organ_rand_sweeps_2.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>

            <p>I then used a trick I've discovered to make samples sound like they're played through an untuned FM radio. I have a collection of samples of just raw radio static. If I use those samples to modulate a delay on my source, the static convincingly changes in amplitude along with the sample.</p>
            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/radio_synth_fft.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>

            <p>In addition to sounding cool, the static gives the next stage something to "chew on." I used the phase vocoder from <a href="https://cycling74.com/tutorials/the-phase-vocoder-–-part-i">Cycling '74's</a> tutorial to time stretch my staticky chords, and the static causes all kinds of nice artifacts in the phase vocoder. After this, I added a little bit of saturation because having <code>fftz.ether~</code> pick the quieter bin can sometimes sound a bit dull.</p>
            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/radio_synth_fft_pvoc.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>

            <h3>Sound 2: noisy/rhythmic</h3>
            <p>On the other side, I started with a sine wave oscillator in gen~ frequency-modulating itself at a single-sample delay (it was this short delay that made me need to use gen~). I used the rand~ object to modulate a number of parameters, including the starting frequency and modulation depth. This produces some nice staticky, rhythmic noises that sound like a very light synthetic snare.</p>
            <p>I then used Logic Pro's "flex time" feature to quantize the result to a 16th note grid (which also adds some nice time stretching artifacts!) </p>
            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/fm-fb-osc-rand_bip.7.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>

            <p>I play two copies (one for left and one for right) of the sample with random modulation of the speed and direction.</p>
            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/fm-fb-osc-rand_bip.7_proc.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>

            <h3>Sound 1 & 2 combined</h3>
            <p>Finally, when I put both the sustained and percussive sources into <code>fftz.ether~</code> the end result sounds like this:</p>
            <audio controls>
                <source src="./media/02-27-2024/spectral_composite_dry.mp3" type="audio/mp3">
            </audio>
            <p>I was going for something to fill out and add activity to the upper register, and I'm very happy with how it turned out.</p>

            <br />
            <h3>Conclusion</h3>
            <p>I want to give a shout out to <a href="https://nathan.ho.name/archive.html">Nathan Ho</a>. I appreciate his blogging about making sounds in SuperCollider, and it's inspired me to do write-ups of my own sound design. </p>
            <p>Today's sounds will be combined with the chord synthesizer I mentioned on Mastodon <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@reillypascal/111773037885275169">last month</a>. All of this is played by the keyboardist, with today's sound (and variants of it using different chords) each being assigned to a single MIDI note. Ideally I would like to be composing more quickly, but I'm teaching a class I've never taught before (Intro to Music Business), in addition to other teaching, so that's been taking up a lot of my time.</p>
            <p>If you'd like to try this for yourself, <a href="https://mega.nz/folder/cLVzHCBZ#SVlAyRb0RPL7sUwnXfke8A">here's</a> a link to the patches and other materials. You'll need the FFTease package and Max 8.</p>
            ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Do Read the Comments</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/01-14-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/01-14-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
            <description>A writeup of using Netlify serverless functions and Supabase to code a comments section on a static site</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
            <p>My blog now has a comment section! Let's talk about how I made it.</p> 
            <p>It uses the <a href="https://supabase.com/">Supabase</a> Postgres database, which bills itself as an "open-source Firebase alternative." There are a number of ways of communicating with the database. I chose the <a href="https://github.com/supabase/supabase-js">supabase-js</a> JavaScript client since I'm familiar with JS, and because I wanted to use Netlify's <a href="https://www.netlify.com/blog/intro-to-serverless-functions/">"serverless" function</a> capabilities to run the code that communicates with the database.</p>

            <p>I considered several ways of getting the comments to display, including embedding a server-side-rendered page in an &lt;iframe&gt;, and using the pre-made "<a href="https://jsrepos.com/repo/a-blazing-fast-lightweight-and-open-source-comment-system-for-your-static-website-blogs-powered-by-supabase">SupaComments</a>" library, but it actually turned out to be easier to just do it myself with vanilla JavaScript. For the full code, see the <a href="https://github.com/reillypascal/personalsite/tree/main/reillyspitzfaden/netlify/functions">Netlify functions</a>, <a href="https://github.com/reillypascal/personalsite/blob/main/reillyspitzfaden/styles/scripts.js">global JS file</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/reillypascal/personalsite/tree/main/reillyspitzfaden/blog">blog posts'</a> HTML files on GitHub. I'll walk through some of the most relevant parts here.</p> 
            
            <br />
            <h3>Handling Comment Submissions</h3>
            <p>In the form submission handler function, I make the form data into a FormData object. I then retrieve the commenter's name, email, and comment, as well as the URL of the blog post on which they're commenting. Note that in the code examples, I have left out the DOM-manipulating code to focus on handling the comment data.</p>

<pre><code class="language-js">// (from scripts.js)
// submit conmment handler - thisPostURL variable is 
// defined in the page that calls this function
const handleSubmitComment = async (event) => {
    event.preventDefault();

    // ... reset "Comment submitted!" message, if one exists

    // get form data
    const myForm = event.target;
    const formData = new FormData(myForm);
    // retrieve the needed fields from the FormData object
    const formObject = {
        name: formData.get("name"),
        email: formData.get("email"),
        postURL: thisPostURL,
        comment: formData.get("comment")
    };
    // ...</code></pre>

                <p>Since I didn't want the extra work of making a new table in my database every time I made a new blog post, I have all the comments go to a single table. Each blog post tags the comments on it with the post's URL, and uses that URL to retrieve only the appropriate comments.</p>

                <p>After the comment is formatted into an object, I use the <code class="language-js" >fetch()</code> API to send the comment data to the serverless function in the body of a POST request.</p>


    <pre><code class="language-js" >    // ... (continued from above)
    // call the serverless function and send it 
    // formObject in the body of the request
    const response = await fetch('/.netlify/functions/set_comment', {
        method: "POST",
        body: JSON.stringify(formObject)
    })
    // ...</code></pre>

                                <p>From there, the rest of the handler prints either a success or error message under the comment submission form.</p>

    <pre><code class="language-js" >    // ... (continued from above)
    .then(response => {
        // ... reset form to indicate comment submitted,
        // and print success message below
    })
    .catch(error => {
        // ... reset form to indicate comment submitted, 
        // and print error message below
    });
};</code></pre>
                            <br />
                            <h3>Handling the Comment Retrieval Button</h3>
                                <p>The handler for retrieving the comments is similar. Note that the body of the POST request only needs the post URL&mdash;this is used to select the comments that were made on a given blog post.</p>

<pre><code class="language-js" >// retrieve conmment handler - thisPostURL is defined in page
const handleGetComments = async (event) => {
    event.preventDefault();

    // ... erase any previously-displayed comments, load spinner .gif

    // call serverless function
    const response = await fetch('/.netlify/functions/get_comment', {
        method:'POST',
        body: JSON.stringify({
            postURL: thisPostURL
        })
    })
    // .json() returns a promise too, so there needs to be another .then()
    .then(response => response.json())
    .then(json => {
        // ... clear the spinner; test if there are any comments 
        // in the returned list; if so, iterate through them 
        // and add the appropriate HTML/text
    })
    .catch(error => {
        // ... clear the spinner; display an error message
    });
}</code></pre>

                            <br />
                            <h3>Supabase: Storing and Retrieving Comments</h3>
                            <p>The serverless functions to interface with Supabase need the 'dotenv' and 'supabase-js' Node packages, which are required from index.js in the root directory.</p>
<pre><code class="language-js" >require('dotenv').config();
require('@supabase/supabase-js');</code></pre>
            <p>In the function files, which are in netlify/functions&mdash;the default directory Netlify specifies&mdash;I get the URL and anon key for the database from Netlify's .env variables. Netlify lets you specify those from your site's console, so it's easy to keep them secure.</p>
<pre><code class="language-js" >const {
    DATABASE_URL,
    SUPABASE_SERVICE_API_KEY
} = process.env;</code></pre>
            <p>The meat of the setter function is the <code class="language-js" >.from()</code> method, which accesses the desired table, and the <code class="language-js" >.insert()</code> method, which adds the new entry. These are specified by the Supabase <a href="https://zone-www-dot-lmn02xr2l-supabase.vercel.app/docs/reference/javascript/select">API</a>. Netlify uses the ES modules default export syntax for the serverless functions, and the functions are automatically named after the files that contain them&mdash;<code class="language-js" >set_comment</code> and <code class="language-js" >get_comment</code> in my case.</p>

<pre><code class="language-js" >// create supabase client using url/anon key from Netlify env variables
const { createClient } = require('@supabase/supabase-js');
const supabase = createClient(DATABASE_URL, SUPABASE_SERVICE_API_KEY);

// uses ES modules syntax for default export
exports.handler = async (event, context, callback) => {
    let data
    try {
        // the result of createClient() can access the database
        data = await supabase
        // 'comments' is the name of the table 
        // within my database; .from() selects that
        .from('comments')
        // .insert() takes an array with one or more objects whose keys correspond
        // to those in the table, and adds each object as a new row to the table
        .insert([
            {   
                name: JSON.parse(event.body).name,
                email: JSON.parse(event.body).email,
                postURL: JSON.parse(event.body).postURL,
                comment: JSON.parse(event.body).comment,
                created_at: ((new Date()).toISOString()).toLocaleString('en-US'),
                show: true
            }
        ])
    } catch (e) {
        return {
            statusCode: 500,
            body: JSON.stringify({
                error: e.message
            })
        }
    }
    return {
        statusCode: 200,
        body: JSON.stringify(data)
    };
}</code></pre>

            <p>The getter function works similarly, but uses the <code class="language-js" >.select()</code> and <code class="language-js" >.eq()</code> methods. These specify the columns to return and a matching condition to indicate whether or not to return a row, respectively.</p>

<pre><code class="language-js" >exports.handler = async (event, context, callback) => {
    let returnVals
    try {
        returnVals = await supabase
        // as in set_comments, retrieves 'comments' table
        .from('comments')
        // selects the desired columns in each row
        .select('name, email, comment, created_at')
        // selects only the rows containing comments 
        // made at the blog post's URL
        .eq('postURL', JSON.parse(event.body).postURL)
        
    } catch (e) {
        return {
            statusCode: 500,
            body: JSON.stringify({
              error: e.message
            })
        }
    }
    return {
        statusCode: 200,
        body: JSON.stringify(returnVals.data)
    };
}</code></pre>
            <br />
            <h3>Conclusions</h3>
            <p>Some of the challenges I had in this project:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>It took me some trial and error to conceptualize exactly what the serverless functions needed to send back and forth with my site/Netlify.</li>
                <li>I had previously directly interfaced form submissions with Netlify for my contact form, but I needed to do a bit of reading to understand exactly how to get the information from the form into a format suitable to send in an HTTP POST request.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>One of my takeaways from this was that I should do more backend stuff. I haven't done much before, but I find it's a lot of fun to connect things together and make them communicate. Maybe a future project could include making my own database on my Raspberry Pi and setting up more complex interactions with it.</p>
            <p>Thanks for reading this far! In the near term, I'm planning to make an RSS feed for this blog&mdash;look for a similar write-up when I do that.</p>
            ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>Hello World!</title>
            <dc:creator>Reilly Spitzfaden</dc:creator>
            <link>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/01-03-2024</link>
            <guid>https://reillyspitzfaden.com/blog/01-03-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
            <description>An introduction to this blog and what I plan to do with it</description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
            <p>Welcome to my blog! I recently listened to <a href="https://localghost.dev/">Sophie Koonin</a>'s talk "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H2Ux0hGQcs4">This Talk Is Under Construction: A Love Letter to the Personal Website</a>," as well as <a href="https://localghost.dev/blog/remembering-the-early-00s-teen-website-scene/">this blog post</a> about the early-aughts teen website scene, and was immediately inspired to do more to make this site into a piece of personal expression. One of the ways I'm doing that is starting this blog, which I'll be using as a free-form journal about my interests and for write-ups of current projects. Some interests include:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Digital signal processing and audio plugin development in C++</li>
                <li>Composition in Max/MSP/gen</li>
                <li>Homemade electronics, often with a musical bent</li>
                <li>Various projects on my Raspberry Pi, including the <a href="https://geminiprotocol.net/">gemini</a> protocol, networking, and more</li>
                <li>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse">Fediverse</a> and "<a href="https://smolweb.org/index.html">smol web</a>" or "small web"</li>
            </ul>
            <p>RSS will likely be coming if I'm able to figure that out, as well as potentially a built-in comments feature. For now, I'll be posting updates to my <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@reillypascal">Mastodon</a> (and if you know me personally, on other personal social media!).</p>
            <p>I hope you'll join me!</p>
            ]]> 
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>